How many of you have got it?
Okay, I will give one copy here
for your library —
you can all share it.
At the outset, I must confess
that the title Gita Enlightened
may be a little misleading.
I by no means profess to
enlighten the Gita,
but I humbly say that it has
been written through enlightened eyes —
eyes that have been enlightened
by Her Holiness Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
So, what happened was, in the
year '81, Shri Mataji was going
to a resort in Coimbatore for
a month, and just by the way
she said, "You want to come?"
Of course — any way I can
be with Shri Mataji.
So we were there in Coimbatore,
just the two of us and nobody else.
I had been talking about the Gita
— having read over a hundred books
on it and heard several discourses
by many self-proclaimed gurus
and so-called eminent intellectuals —
and I had only gotten more confused.
It was at this turning point in
my life that destiny brought me
to the feet of Her Holiness.
And when I questioned her on
these subtle points of the Gita,
its apparent contradictions,
its juxtapositions,
she so simply and with such
profound wisdom threw immense
light on them that I recognized
what a storehouse of knowledge she is.
I had been writing things about
the Gita, and she said,
"Okay, now forget everything
that you have read or written
about the Gita."
And she started from the very
beginning — and the beginning
was completely different
from everything else.
She said, "It's all about Draupadi.
It's all about chastity.
It's all about the Ganesh Tatva."
The first and foremost thing we
have to understand is that
Shri Krishna is a divine incarnation,
and He came at a time
when we needed to understand
the essence of dharma.
For example, I have been quite
surprised by the way people
explain Him. As far as Ahimsa
is concerned, they have preached
it to such an extent that we
have to look after all the
mosquitoes of Delhi.
Such absurd things people have
deduced from what Krishna
tried to emphasize in the Shri Gita.
And this itself explained to me
what Lord Krishna meant when
Arjuna asked Him which of the
two paths is greater —
the path of Jnana or the path
of Bhakti.
Lord Krishna, although He said
that both lead to the same goal,
in the end says, "The one who
loves Me is dear to Me."
Now, this may have escaped the
attention of many readers —
that having said both paths lead
to the same goal, why does
He then say this?
Because in this very verse
lies the whole secret:
that the knowledge we seek
through our intellect is limited.
It is our limited intelligence,
because it is the intelligence
of the individual and therefore
limited by his ego.
So it was the Ganesh Tatva that
is the basis of everything,
and when that is insulted,
then the Shakti —
the intervention of the Divine —
takes place.
One example: at the time of the
war, Karna — the great,
generous man, very well known
for his virtues —
got caught up in a wheel of
his chariot and could not
get his leg out.
When Arjuna faced him and
raised his Gandiva, Karna
challenged him, saying,
"A chivalrous person,
a fellow warrior — in dharma,
when I have no weapons on me,
you cannot kill me with
your weapons."
At that moment, Shri Krishna
pointed at him and said,
"Kill him. Where were his
warrior virtues when
Draupadi was insulted?
Draupadi's insult was the
greatest sin that was committed,
and what was he doing at
that time?"
And Arjuna killed Karna.
This is dharma.
He is called Leeladhara — the
one for whom the whole world
is a play. And that's why He
says, "They are already killed."
That doesn't mean you start
killing people, becoming violent,
because you don't agree
with someone.
Only Shri Krishna can say
whom to kill.
You have to be a realized soul
to understand why Shri Krishna
had to ask Arjuna to kill,
and why the Goddess had to
kill so many demons.
But the idea today is that we
should try to be sympathetic
even towards demons, towards
the devils who are spreading
Asurividya everywhere — that
we should be sympathetic
with all people, that there
is good in everyone.
That's not Krishna's message.
He showed His love by killing
the demons.
So it's all about the chastity
of Draupadi being challenged
by Duryodhana. That's where
it started.
So the whole angle was completely
different — nobody had ever
given this interpretation of
the Gita before.
It started with Ganesha, and
then it went from one chakra
to another, to the Vishuddhi,
and then beyond the Vishuddhi.
What surprised me most about
what Shri Krishna said —
and what she explained — was this:
"But they are already dead."
Shri Krishna said, "I have
already killed them.
What are you doing, Arjuna?
You do nothing.
You think you are going to
kill them? I have already killed them."
So I said, "But how are they
dead? They are alive,
they are on the battlefield."
She said, "They are dead
because their spirit has been betrayed."
And the war started. Arjuna
actually became nervous,
I would say, and said, "I would
not like to fight my own
kith and kin, and my gurus."
So Shri Krishna says, "They
are already dead. They are killed.
These are already dead people —
their eyes are not open.
Whom are you going to kill here?
You just have to remove
some people from this earth
to establish dharma."
Now, the idea of dharma,
according to us, is some sort
of Hinduism, or Islam, or
some other "-ism." It is not.
In a human being — just as
carbon has four valencies —
dharma has ten valencies.
And when a person falls from
these, he loses his powers
as a human being.
When you betray your spirit,
you are dead, because you
have no use to evolution —
you have gone out of evolution,
like the dinosaurs who went
out of evolution.
So whether your physical body
is there or not makes no
difference to the Divine.
That was the very deep
essence of the Gita.
So then she said, "All right —
even in Sahaja Yoga,
nobody is going to tell
you, do this."
So — you've done this, why did
you wear jeans to a puja,
and so forth?
You have a free hand,
do what you want.
But if you go against the
spirit, you will lose your vibrations.
You are the loser.
So I said, but Arjuna had this
vision of Shri Krishna —
the Virata — yet he still had
doubts in his mind,
he was still asking questions.
If you see God but you don't
have the recognition,
you will miss it.
So the point, she says, is not
to see God — I mean,
the point is not to have
a vision of God.
"People see me every day,"
she said, "but they don't believe in me.
You have to discover your own
kundalini, your own divinity.
Then you will know who I am."
Unless and until you experience
your own spirit, how can
you experience God?
So the point was not to see
the Virata — the point was
to experience your own spirit.
That is the thing.
You think you know God,
but you don't know God.
You have a concept of God —
that God is this, God is that —
you make an idol, you make
a murti, but God is not that.
That is your concept of God,
and you may worship that concept,
but that is not the reality.
That doesn't mean you're
following God.
Even in Greek mythology, they
humanized their gods,
and then those gods fight
with each other,
each claiming their god is
superior to the other's.
But the question isn't whose
God is superior.
The question isn't whether
God is on your side.
The question is: are you
on God's side?
And how will you know you
are on God's side?
All these fanatics, all these
terrorists, all these fundamentalists —
they say they are doing
God's work.
But how do you know you're
doing God's work?
You're only pampering your own
ego, only following your own ego.
You'll only know when you know
yourself, when you know your own spirit.
And the person who knows his
own spirit can never be a fanatic,
can never be a fundamentalist —
because the spirit is the same
in everyone, and if you have
felt your own spirit,
you will not hurt that same
spirit in another person.
We are different bodies,
but the spirit is the same.
That is what she explained
is the essence of the Gita.
So Arjuna is blinded by his
attachment to his relationships
in the enemy ranks — his teachers,
Dronacharya, Bhishma Pitamaha,
and all that.
He's not able to come out of
that; he doesn't want to hurt them.
He says, "How can I kill them?
They are my this,
they are my that," all that.
This is emotional attachment.
So we can say that through
the right side, you get
attachment to the ego, when
you get fixed ideas,
or you get attached to an
ideology — "this is communism,
this is democracy, this is that."
But there's also the attachment
to your super-ego —
"this is my relation, this is
this, this is that."
Both have to be overcome.
We have to get detached from both.
But that doesn't mean you
become a dry personality.
You enjoy everybody, but you're
not attached to anybody —
that is the thing.
Earlier, you were very curious
about everybody —
"What is he doing? What is that?" —
and now you're only curious about God.
So all other curiosities are gone.
When you become attached to
the curiosity of God,
you get detached from all
other curiosities.
Nothing else matters. "Oh, he's
doing this — let him do it.
He's this — so what?
He's a minister — so what?"
Nothing, nothing, nothing.
That's like that bhajan
of Shankaracharya — tadakim,
tadakim — "this, not this."
It's there. You're not blind
to it, but you're not attached to it.
So that was the Gita. She said,
"Call it Gita Enlightened" —
that this Gita, which has been
misunderstood, which has been
parroted without self-realization,
has now become enlightened.
Now you can understand.
Only a Sahaja Yogi can
understand the message
of Shri Krishna. But then she
added that Shri Krishna
gave realization to only
one person, to Arjuna.
Arjuna saw Him as a very huge,
big personality,
and saw in Him all human beings
and all creation moving about,
and he couldn't bear it anymore —
he said, "I don't want to see it again."
Shri Krishna spoke the Gita
only to Arjuna,
only to one person — He didn't
tell it to even a second person,
because He was born six
thousand years ago,
and at that time people's
maturity was so low
that He did not tell it to
anybody else but Arjuna.
This was heard by another
person who wrote it down —
Vyasa is the poet who
wrote about it.
But now the time has come — the
"blossom time," as she calls it —
when thousands can give
realization, en masse.
Giving one person realization
doesn't change anything.
If you want to change the
world, it has to happen
en masse, all over the world.
And that is what Sahaja Yoga
is doing, and it has made a difference.
It has brought much greater
awareness into human consciousness.
A lot of things that people
were earlier not sensitive to,
now they are.
This is the change that has
taken place, and things are changing —
things are moving very fast.
People are getting exposed
very fast; negativity is
getting exposed very fast.
Earlier it was not like that.
So it's not that negativity
isn't there — it is there,
but it's getting exposed.
So many scandals are
getting exposed.
All these things which are
against the Muladhara,
which have been going on in
social media —
now countries are banning them.
They say this is bad for young
people, because there's
a certain level of awareness now.
Earlier, people were oblivious
of it. So all this is now coming.
Sahaja Yoga is bringing this
global transformation,
and that is what we call the
power of Shri Kalki —
the power of Shri Kalki is your
power, working collectively.
It is not a power of destruction;
it is a power of transformation.
A great movement of evolution
is taking place through all
of you, each one of you —
wherever you are,
things are getting transformed.
You will not even know it.
But your presence... At a
mundane level, I'll say
that if you go into an office,
people notice you.
They want to sit next to you,
they want to talk to you,
because they feel a kind of
relaxation when they are
talking to you.
Then they ask you, "What is it
that you are doing?
You are always so calm, you
are always so relaxed,
and we feel very happy in
your presence." It's felt like that.
But at a global level, it is
working through all the
governments, through all the
heads of government,
and very fast — even with wars.
People are now understanding
the futility of war.
Earlier, the powerful countries
thought, "We are the most
powerful, we can do
anything we want."
War is not the way.
War is not the way to win —
they have realized that.
They used to say that power
flows through the barrel of a gun.
Not anymore. It flows through
your kundalini, through your
love, through self-realization.
This is the future of humanity,
and this will save humanity.
God did not create this world
to be destroyed.
Shri Krishna played holy
to spread joy —
to be joyous. That is the
message of the Gita. Okay?
Jai Shri Mataji. Jai Shri Mataji.